<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude'">
]>
<refentry id="CrystFEL-coding-standards">
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle role="top_of_page" id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.top_of_page">CrystFEL coding standards</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo>
  Coding  standards
</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv></refnamediv>


<refsect1 id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.description" role="desc">
<title role="desc.title">Summary</title>
<para>
This page documents the coding conventions used within the CrystFEL source code.  Read these to help when reading the code or before making modifications destined to be sent upstream.
</para>
</refsect1>


<refsect1 id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.license">
<title>Licensing and copyright</title>
<para>
CrystFEL is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License version 3 or higher.  Contributions are very welcome provided they also use this license.
</para>
<para>
Whenever you edit a source file, don't forget to update the copyright dates at the top.  Add your name and email address if they're not there already.  Be sure to add your name to the 'AUTHORS' file in the top level folder, as well.
</para>
</refsect1>


<refsect1 id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.formatting">
<title>Formatting</title>
<para>
<emphasis>Indentation</emphasis> is done with <emphasis>tabs</emphasis> and
<emphasis>alignment</emphasis> is done with spaces.  This way, the code looks
neat whatever width you configure your editor to display tabs as.
</para>
<para>
However, code must be <emphasis>strictly</emphasis> wrapped at 80 columns, or
what would be 80 columns if the tabs were displayed as 8 spaces.
If you think you need more width, you're at too many levels of indentation and
need to break things down a bit.
</para>
</refsect1>


<refsect1 id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.brackets">
<title>Brackets and so on</title>
<para>
Brackets and so on should go like this:
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
/* Multiple line comments have stars
 * down one side */
void somefunction(int someparam)
{
	/* Single line comments use this style (not //) */
	if ( a &lt; b ) {
		/* 'if' statements usually have the opening brace on the same
		 * line as the condition. */
	} else {
		/* 'else's are 'cuddled' */
	}

	if ( some &amp;&amp; very &amp;&amp; long &amp;&amp; condition &amp;&amp; that &amp;&amp; spans
	     &amp;&amp; two &amp;&amp; lines )
	{
		/* Opening brace is on a line by itself in the case of a very
		 * long condition */
	}
}

/* Comments use proper capitalisation to make things look neat */
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
'struct' blocks can have the braces like functions or 'if' statements.  Usually
the former looks nicer if the struct is large.
</para>
</refsect1>


<refsect1 id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.cleverness">
<title>Cleverness</title>
<para>
Yes, we all know you can insert a new node into an RB-tree while simultaneously
calculating Pi to 150 decimal places in one line of code.  You don't need to
prove it here.  As a general rule, if you think you're about to do something clever, <emphasis>don't do it at all</emphasis>.
</para>
</refsect1>


<refsect1 id="CrystFEL-coding-standards.evilness">
<title>Evil dictator</title>
<para>
Despite your following all of the above, I will probably still touch up your
code in some places while (or shortly after) integrating it into mainline
CrystFEL.  Please try not to take it personally.
</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
